A Guide to the Paul Ehrlich and Martha Marquardt papers (Wellcome collection) FA136
Rockefeller Archive Center
Paul Ehrlich and Martha Marquardt papers (Wellcome collection)
1863-1956
Rockefeller Archive Center
Marquardt, Martha
Ehrlich, Paul
FA136
20 Cubic Feet
Biographical/Historical note
Paul Ehrlich, 1854-1915, physician and scientist, Berlin and Frankfurt, Germany. Founder of hematology, pioneer and major contributor to the fields of histochemistry and immunology. Famous for his development of chemotherapy (arsphenamine - 606) for syphilis. Nobel Laureate in physiology or medicine in 1908, jointly with Elie Metchnikoff for their studies in immunology.
Martha Marquardt, 1873-1956, secretary to Paul Ehrlich from 1902-1915. Author of two books about Paul Ehrlich, "Paul Ehrlich" als Mensch und Arbeiter", 1924. "Paul Ehrlich" in English 1949 and in German 1950. Moving force behind the publication of "The Collected Papers of Paul Ehrlich", 1956 and transcriber of 47 volumes of Paul Ehrlich's copy-books. Author of various plays and articles.
Scope and Contents note
This special collection of the Rockefeller University pertains to two individual. The material was sorted accordingly into two distinct collections, entitled "Paul Ehrlich Material" and "Martha Marquardt Material".
The collection consists of letters received by Paul Ehrlich, a synopsis of their contents, handwritten manuscripts by Paul Ehrlich, contracts between Ehrlich-Behring and Hoechst. Handwritten notes and "blocks" by Ehrlich. Reprints, photographs, paper cuttings and obituary notices. The collection contains some Paul Ehrlich memorabilia and an oil painting.
The Martha Marquardt part of the collection contains voluminous correspondence, letters received by Martha Marquardt as well as carbon copies of letters written by her. It contains material regarding her two books about Paul Ehrlich, many articles and plays she wrote, as well as a film she made about flies. There are many photographs of Martha Marquardt, her family and friends. There are some reprints and books and because of her long-standing friendship with Sir Almroth Wright, there are some items concerning him.
Custodial History note
The material in the combined collection was in Martha Marquardt's possession at the time of her death in 1956. Many of the items in the "Paul Ehrlich Material" were sent to her after World War II, when she had emigrated to England. These items had been stored in Geneva, where Mrs. Hedwig Ehrlich had fled to in 1939. A list of articles from the "Geneva Chest" is part of this collection (Box 2a, Folder 1). Many of these items on this list have been deposited at The Rockefeller University Archives by the 2 grandsons of Paul Ehrlich, Hans and Günther Schwerin, in 1978.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The papers and memorabilia of Paul Ehrlich and Martha Marquardt were deposited, with The Rockefeller University Archives in May 1980 by the Trustees of the will of Sir Henry Solomon Wellcome.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 650.3 Eh89
Conditions Governing Access note
Written permission must be obtained from the Head of Donor Relations/Collection Development of the Rockefeller Archive, or an applicable designee, in order to access the collection.
Marquardt, Martha; Ehrlich, Paul
- Paul Ehrlich Material, 1
  Biographical/Historical note
  Biographical Note
  1854 Born March 14 in Strehlen, Silesia, of Jewish parents
  1872 Graduated from Maria Magdalena Gymnasium in Breslau
  1878 M. D. from the University of Leipzig, after studies at the Universities of Breslau, Strassburg and Freiburg
  1878 Assistant physician at the Charité Hospital in Berlin, (later senior physician)
  1882 Received the Professor title from the state
  1883 Married Hedwig Pinkus
  1884 Birth of daughter Stefanie
  1886 Birth of daughter Marianne
  1887 Became Privat Docent (Lecturer); Resigned from post at the Charité Hospital
  1888 Without formal position. Because of contracted tuberculosis cured in Italy and Egypt for some months
  1889 Return to Berlin, establishing a private research laboratory
  1890 Became Ausserordentlicher Professor at the University of Berlin
  1891 Received a post holding clinical responsibilities at the Moabit Hospital in Berlin.; Was offered laboratory space by Robert Koch in the new Institute for Infectious Diseases where most of the immunology work was done
  1896 Was made Director of the State Institute for Serum Research and Serum Control in Steglitz. Became Geheimer Medicinal Rath
  1899 Move of the Institute to Frankfurt, renamed to Institute for Experimental Therapy
  1906 Addition of the Georg Speyer-Haus to the Institute for continued research on chemotherapy
  1907 Became Geheimer Obermedicinal Rath
  1908 Received the Nobel Prize in Physiology or Medicine, sharing it with Elie Metchnikoff for their contributions to immunology
  1910 First report on Salvarsan treatment for syphilis
  1911 Became Wirklicher Geheimrath with the title of Excellency
  1914 Was made Ordentlicher Professor at the newly established University of Frankfurt
  1915 Died August 20
  Honorary Degrees
  1904 University of Chicago, LL.D.
  1907 University of Oxford, D.C.L.
  1911 University of Athens, Dr. phil. h.c.
  1911 University of Breslau, Dr. med. h.c.
  Awards
  1887 Tiedemann Prize
  1903 The Prussian Golden Medal of Science
  1906 Prize of Honor at the XVth International Congress of Medicine at Lisbon
  1908 Nobel Prize
  1911 Leibig Medal
  1914 Cameron Prize of the University of Edinburgh
  Paul Ehrlich was made honorary, corresponding or foreign member to some 83 international scientific societies.
  - Incoming Correspondence
    Arrangement note
    Arranged in alphabetical order.
    - Abderhalden, E., 1900; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Adami, George, 1907; 1 letter, typescript and handwritten (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Adler, C., 1910; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Albrecht, Eugen, 1907; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Althoff, Friedrich, 1900-1907; 8 items: 3 handwritten letters; 3 calling cards (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Adickes, Franz, 1906; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Arrhenius, Savante, 1902-1904; 9 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Aschaffenburg, 1910; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Aschoff, Ludwig, 1902; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Ascoli, Maurizio, 1900 1911; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Baginski, 1902; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Bagshave, Arthur, 1909 1912; 2 letters, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Bashford, 1901; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Behring, Emil, 1892-1905; 45 handwritten letters + 1 envelope (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Scope and Contents note
      Typed by Martha Marquardt listing 7 letters regarding authors' opinions about Behring.
      Letters are now filed in alphabetical order.
    - Bertheim, Alfred, 1908; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Bethe, Albert, 1899-1910; 7 letters, handwritten and typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Benario, J., 1892-1910; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Berliner, Arnold, 1903; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Bier, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Bodenstein, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Bonhoff, 1900; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - Bordet, Jules, 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 22)
    - Borrel, 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 23)
    - Brauer, Ludoph, 1908; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 24)
    - Breinl, A., 1908 1909; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 25)
    - Brieger, (Ludwig?), 1892; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 26)
    - Browning, Carl, 1908; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 27)
    - Bruce, David, typescript, signed by D. C. Dandy for Bruce, 1906; 1 letter (Box 1, Folder 28)
    - Buchner, Hans, 1894 1900; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 29)
    - Bulloch, William, 1899-1902; 6 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 30)
    - Bumm, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 31)
    - Bürgi, Emil, 1905 (?); 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 32)
    - Calmette, Albert, 1902-1909; 5 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 33)
    - Chiaruttini, P.E. to Chiaruttini, undated; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 34)
    - Cloetta, M., 1905 1907; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 35)
    - Cohn, Ferdinand, 1890; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 36)
    - Cole, Rufus, 1910; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 37)
    - Councilman, William, 1904 1905; 2 letters, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 38)
    - Christy, Thomas & Co., 1897; 2 letters, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 39)
    - Dönitz, Wilhelm, 1900-1901; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 40)
    - Dowson, W., 1904; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 41)
    - Dunham, Edward, 1904; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 42)
    - Edinger, Ludwig, 1903-1909; 4 letters, handwritten and typescript with signature (Box 1, Folder 43)
    - Flexner, Simon, typescript with signature; 2 translations, 1 copy of Ehrlich letter to Flexner, 1902-1910; 8 letters (Box 1, Folder 44)
    - Fleischer, Richard, 1906; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 45)
    - Förster, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 46)
    - Freund, Wilhelm, 1904; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 47)
    - Frankl, A., 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 48)
    - Frankfurter Zeitung, 1910; 1 letter, typescript (Box 1, Folder 49)
    - Fulda, Ludwig, 1905; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 50)
    - Fütterer, G., 1904; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 51)
    - Gaffky, Georg, 1907; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 52)
    - Gavazzeni, Alessandro, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 53)
    - Goldmann, E., 1906-1911; 6 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 54)
    - Gottlieb, R., 1897; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Goldscheider, 1898 1908; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 56)
    - Gruber, Max, 1900; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 57)
    - Halberstaedter, L., 1910?; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 58)
    - Hata, Sahashiro, 1910-1915; 3 letters (Box 1, Folder 59)
      1 handwritten letter by Hata to Ehrlich; 2 copies of letters by Ehrlich to Hata.
    - Heffter, A., 1906; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 60)
    - Heidenhain, Martin, 1902; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 61)
    - Herter, Christian, 1906; 1 letter, One 7 page typescript letter with signature, of which pages 2, 3 and 4 are missing (Box 1, Folder 62)
    - Heubner, W., 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 63)
    - Hertwig, R., 1904; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 64)
    - Herxheimer, Karl, 1907; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 65)
    - Hoffmann, E., 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 66)
    - Itajuba, Baron de (Brazilian Embassy), 1895; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 67)
    - Iversen, Julius, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 68)
    - Jendrassin, Ernst, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 69)
    - Katz, J. R., 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 70)
    - Kirchner, 1900; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 71)
    - Kitasato, Shibasaburo, 1898-1910; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 72)
    - Klemperer, G., 1899 1906; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 73)
    - Klugt, Ed, 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 74)
    - Koch, Robert, 1903-1908; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 75)
    - Kohn, Richard, 1892; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 76)
    - Kolonialamt - Berlin, 3 typescript letters regarding trypanosomiasis in East Africa with 2 different signatures (Golinelli 1x; Dernburg 2x), 1908-1910; 3 letters (Box 1, Folder 77)
    - Kossel, Albrecht, 1903 1910; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 78)
    - Kraus, F., undated; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 79)
    - Kyes, Preston, 1904; 4 letters, 1 handwritten letter by Kyes, with a typescript translation of this letter; 2 typescript translations of missing original letters (Box 1, Folder 80)
    - Lafont, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 81)
    - Lamb, E., 1903; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 82)
    - Langmann, G., 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 83)
    - Laubenheimer, August, 1890-1900; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 84)
    - Laveran, Charles L. A., 1905-1910; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 85)
    - Levaditi, Constantin, 1902-1908; 12 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 86)
    - Lesser, E., 1904; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 87)
    - Liesegans, Raphael, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 88)
    - Lippmann, Edmund v., 1902; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 89)
    - Loeb, Jacques, 1907; 1 letter, typescript copy (?), no signature (Box 1, Folder 90)
    - Lubarsch, O., 1894 1907; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 91)
    - Lustig, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 1, Folder 92)
    - Madsen, Thorvald, 1899-1904; 12 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - MacFadyen, Allan, 1901; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Magnus, R., 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Marie, Pierre, 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Mamorek, 1903; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Meirowsky, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Mecklenburg, Herzog Adolf zu, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Mendel, 1891; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Metschnikoff, Elie, 1899-1910; 4 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Meys, 1899; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 10)
    - Meyer, Hans, 1903; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Minister of Education and Medical Affairs, Ehrlich to minister, 1905; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Moalton, Fletcher, 1908; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Morgenroth, Julius, 1900-1908; 7 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Morpurgo, B., 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Muir, Robert, 1899; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Müller, Friedrich, 1903 1907; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Naegeli-Naef, Otto, 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Naunyn, Bernhard, 1900-1910; 4 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 19)
    - Neisser, Albert, 1890-1910; 16 letters, handwritten and typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 20)
    - Neisser, Ernst, 1899; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 21)
    - Neisser, Max, 1905; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 22)
    - Nernst, Walther, 1904 1908; 2 letters, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 23)
    - Neufeld, F., 1910; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 24)
    - Nicolle, Charles, 1903 1904; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 25)
    - Nocht, 1909; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 26)
    - Novy, F. G., 1904; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 27)
    - Nothnagel, H., 1893-1905; 3 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 28)
    - Nuttall, George, 1909; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 29)
    - Osler, William, 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 30)
    - Oppersdorf, Graf von, 1906; 2 letters, typescript with signature; printed minutes of a session in parliament (Box 2, Folder 31)
    - Paltauf, Richard, 1901; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 32)
    - Pavlinoff, C., 1906; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 33)
    - Pfeiffer, Richard, 1899-1909; 14 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 34)
    - Pinkus, Felix, 1895; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 35)
    - Pirquet, Clemens von, 1905 1909; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 36)
    - Plimmer, H. G., 1901; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 37)
    - Provaczek, undated, and 1909; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 38)
    - Rabinowitsch, Marcus, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 39)
    - Rathenau, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - Rieder, Robert, 1905; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Roscoe, Henry, 1907; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - Ross, Ronald, 1907; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Roux, Emile, 1903-1904; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 44)
    - Sahli, 1902; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 45)
    - Salomonsen, Carl, 1900-1908; 4 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Sauerbruch, F., 1908; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Schilling, 1908; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Schlossmann, Arthur, 1908; 1 letter, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Schmidt, F., 1904; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 50)
    - Schmidt, Moritz, 1902; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 51)
    - Semple, D., 1906; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 52)
    - Sherrington, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 53)
    - Shiga, Kiyoshi, 1910; 2 letters, typescript with signature (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Spiro, Karl, 1901; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 55)
    - Semon, Felix, 1902; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 56)
    - Studt, 1901; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 57)
    - Terry, Benjamin, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 58)
    - Veit, J., 1901; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 59)
    - Vereinigte Chemische Werke, Charlottenburg, 1906; 1 letter (Box 2, Folder 60)
      Scope and Contents
      typescript copy of Ehrlich letter (original with Himmelweit - Note by Martha Marquardt)
    - Waldeyer, Heinrich, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 61)
    - Wassermann, August, 1894-1909; 30 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 62)
    - Wechsberg, 1901; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 63)
    - Weichert, Wolfgang, 1900 1904; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 64)
    - Weigert, Carl, 1890-1904; 14 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 65)
    - Weinberg, Arthur von, 1909 1915; 2 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 66)
    - Wilbur, Ray, undated; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 67)
    - Willstätter, Richard, 1903-1908; 6 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 68)
    - Windaus, A., 1905; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 69)
    - Wright, Almroth, 1899-1910; 8 letters, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 70)
    - Zangger, 1904; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 71)
    - Zsigmondy, R., 1902; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 72)
    - Zudlitz, 1909; 1 letter, handwritten (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Synopses of incoming correspondence (Box 2a, Folder 1)
    Martha Marquardt made a synopsis of the letters after they were sent to the Wellcome Museum in London. The letters had been taken by Hedwig Ehrlich to Geneva and stored there until their transferal was requested by Mr. Günther Schwerin. This is indicated by a cover sheet which reads: Contents of letters to Ehrlich in the chest which was sent from Geneva to the Wellcome Museum, London, by request to Mr. Günther Schwerin, New York. There is a bound copy of this synopsis, 3 typescript copies. A photocopy was made to check the letters received against this synopsis. Some letters listed in the synopsis are missing; others were removed and placed in more appropriate places within this collection.
    Typed list of contents from the Geneva chest, 6 pages.
  - Contracts between Ehrlich-Behring-Hoechst (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Contract between Hoechst and Ehrlich re: production of Diphtheria antitoxin, dated March 22, 1894, sig. by Laubenheimer. Handwritten promise by Ehrlich to give Behring 2/3 of proceeds after 1897, dated April 15, 1894
    - Handwritten contract by Ehrlich, explaining which experimental animals belong to Ehrlich and which to Behring, undated
  - Behring Denkschrift, 1906 May 6 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    essay in which Behring puts forth his reasons why there should be a central state institute for research to develop therapeutic agents for infectious diseases. Addressed to Althoff who sent it to Ehrlich with comments on margin, 13 pages, dated May 6, 1906. Typescript copy by Martha Marquardt.
  - Papers dealing with Behring's request to have his "Tulase" tested by Ehrlich, 1906 December 18 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    handwritten copy (Abschrift) of Behring's request to Althoff that Ehrlich test his "Tulase", also a copy of Althoff s request to review the matter, presumably to Ehrlich, also typescript copy of Behring's request. Typescript letter by Eilsberger to Ehrlich, dated Dec. 18, 1906 re: Ehrlich's testing of Behring's Tulase-Lactin. Also typescript copy.
  - Announcement letters of honorary memberships to societies; honorary doctor, and Nobel Prize
    - untitled (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Typescript letter announcing that Ehrlich was elected a member of the Imperial Health Council, dated July 4, 1910, issued by the Imperial Chancellor; another letter dated July 14, 1910 announcing the same appointment, issued by the Minister of Educational and Medical Affairs, Steinmetz signed.
    - Letter announcing honorary membership of Paul Ehrlich to the Therapeutic Society of the University of Moscow, dated April 25, 190?. Letter announcing foreign membership of Paul Ehrlich in the Royal Scientific Society of Göttingen, dated Oct. 14, 1904. Pamphlet in Latin announcing honorary doctor for Paul Ehrlich 1907 (Oxford U?) (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Letter announcing the Nobel Prize for Paul Ehrlich, dated Oct. 29, 1908, 1908 October 29 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Letter announcing honorary membership to the German Tropical Medical Society, 1910 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Manuscripts
    - Paul Ehrlich. "Über den jetztigen Stand der Lehre von eosinophilen Zellen", 1904; Handwritten manuscript, 47 pages, 2 typescript copies (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Paul Ehrlich. "Über die Diazo Reaction im Harn", 1900; Handwritten manuscript, 33 pages, 1 typescript copy (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Paul Ehrlich notations on covers, 1899 April (Box 3, Folder 10)
    Hardcover of folder with notations by Paul Ehrlich. 1 copy of Deutsche Rundschau, April 1899, with Paul Ehrlich notations on backcover.
  - Paul Ehrlich letters and blocks (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - 14 handwritten letters by Paul Ehrlich mostly addressed to "Sehr geehrter and lieber herr doctor" (Ludwig Benda?), 1902-1910
      Some are dated.
    - 1 photocopy of a handwritten letter by Paul Ehrlich dated 1887, responding to the receipt of the Tiedemann Prize. 1 typescript translation
    - Letters, 6 pages
      Photocopy of Paul Ehrlich condolence letter to Mrs. Laubenheimer, 1904. Typescript copy of Paul Ehrlich letter to Wassermann, July 9, 1907, re: Behring.
    - 4 pieces of scrap paper with mathematical formulas, presumably in Paul Ehrlich's hand
    - Blocks, 1910-1911
      8 blue blocks, entitled "Erziehungsproblem der Zukunft", 7 yellow, 2 beige (one of which is the original one to Sir Henry Dale, reprinted in Martha Marquardt's book, Paul Ehrlich). 5 yellow blocks, 5 white full size blocks.
    - Matters relating to 606
      - Letter, dated 1911 December 20 (Box 3, Folder 11)
        Typescript, not signed, "Zur Geschichte des Atoxyls", handwritten notation at the margin is not in Paul Ehrlich's handwriting. 2 copies.
      - 6 typewritten pages, some with Paul Ehrlich's notations (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - untitled, 2 photocopies of blocks (Box 3, Folder 11)